<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Advice to the patrons of the test</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26472</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A662A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9714</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11906649</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11906649</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50707</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26472)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50707)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 805:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Advice to the patrons of the test</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>2 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Supporting a repeal of the Test act.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Test Act (1673)</term>
               <term>Criminal law --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religion and law --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:50707:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50707:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
            <head>ADVICE to the Patrons of the TEST</head>
            <p>I Cannot but admire the Heat and Zeal of many Men, (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſome of the Honourable <hi>Houſe of Commmons,</hi>) who, to Support the <hi>Church of England,</hi> unhappily take ſuch meaſures, which in all probability muſt deſtroy That which they ſo Vehemently endeavour to maintain. 'Tis true, <hi>Vox Populi</hi> had once a great Influence; but now, ſince we have a Prince ſo <hi>Religious,</hi> whom none but <hi>Atheiſts</hi> can diſlike; and ſo <hi>Juſt,</hi> whom none but <hi>Traytors</hi> can fear; Give me leave to ſay, That no People in the World are ſo Unjuſt to their Sovereign, or ſo Unkind to themſelves, as thoſe pretended Patriots, who ſo obſtinately promote the continuing of the <hi>Penal Laws for Religion,</hi> eſpecially the <hi>TEST,</hi> I mean that of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> whoſe very Name alone one would think were ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to Damn it.</p>
            <p>For ſure I am, no honeſt <hi>Church of England-man</hi> can have the Confidence to Vindicate that Man, or his Principles, who meerly out of Malice to His preſent Majeſty (whom God long preſerve) and not out of any kindneſs to the <hi>Church of England,</hi> was the only Contriver of that <hi>Machine,</hi> which in It contains, or at leaſt aims at almoſt as much <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> as the <hi>Alchoran,</hi> and ought to be as much Exploded by any Man that pretends to the Name of a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>I have often taken notice of the Common Scandal the <hi>Engliſh Clergy,</hi> without any colour of Truth, throw upon <hi>Catholicks,</hi> &amp; That they are the moſt Severe and Sanguinary People imaginable in the Propagation of Religion; And then for inſtance, my Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Parſon is pleaſed to urge the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> and the Nick-nam'd Perſecution of <hi>France,</hi> all of his own knowledge, tho' he never was o'th' other ſide the Water, unleſs at <hi>Surrey Aſſizes</hi> to Proſecute ſome Litigious Action againſt his Pariſhioners. Such Men would do well to conſider the Rigour of the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> of this Kingdom againſt <hi>Catholicks,</hi> and then I am ſure they'l be of another mind; For I defie any Impartial Man to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance a greater <hi>Perſecution</hi> of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> than that of the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> againſt <hi>Catholicks.</hi> If we enquire into the <hi>Statutes</hi> made ſince <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII. about <hi>Religion.</hi> 'Tis true, under <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> and many other <hi>Roman Emperours, Chriſtians</hi> have been put to Death, and to the moſt Exquiſit Torments imaginable; But in theſe <hi>Statutes, Death</hi> in compariſon is the leaſt Puniſhment; For thereby a <hi>Catholick,</hi> (tho' an <hi>Engliſh-man,</hi> and of a plentiful For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,) is made incapable of Enjoying his Eſtate, and his own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Right and Property, the Son of Inheriting his Father; and in
<pb facs="tcp:50707:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50707:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:50707:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->fine, his Wife and Children turn'd out of Dores to beg their Bread: Yet all this while the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are the only Peaceable, and Charitable Men in the World. Indeed I could wiſh they were ſo, for then thoſe Laws would ſoon be Aboliſh'd: But on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, I find they would Proſecute all other Men with the greateſt rigour. Tho' they cry out of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Perſecution,</hi> when they feel the leaſt Reſtraint upon themſelves; a very great Injuſtice, and ſuch as all good Men ought to bluſh at.</p>
            <p>Of the ſame ſtamp are all the other Calumnies, and Malicious Stories impoſed upon the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> by <hi>B. S. T. S.</hi> and many other Celebrated <hi>Raby's</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant Communion,</hi> who, inſtead of Argument, endeavour to repreſent <hi>Catholicks</hi> as the greateſt Blockheads in the World, if all were true they ſay; But ſince they themſelves know 'tis all falſe, I am ſatisfy'd that Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter belongs to themſelves; For by ſuch <hi>Romances,</hi> inſtead of Preaching the Goſpel, they (beſides aſp<gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſing the King,) Ridicule <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> it ſelf, and endeavour, (as much as in them lies,) to introduce <hi>Atheiſm.</hi> Pardon this ſhort Digreſſion, and be pleaſed to conſider one thing further, That the Government of <hi>England</hi> is abſolutely <hi>Monarchical,</hi> and that the <hi>Prerogative</hi> of the <hi>Crown</hi> can't be Diminiſh'd, even <hi>ſi le Roy le veut.</hi> Now this being gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, (which I'm ſure no Gentleman of the Long Robe will deny,) I would gladly know whether <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> (that great <hi>Diana</hi> of the unthinking Croud,) <hi>Charta Foreſte,</hi> the Statutes of <hi>Metron, Marlebridge, Glouceſter, Acton-Burnell, Weſtminſter</hi> the <hi>2d, Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter, Quia Emptores Terrarum,</hi> &amp;c. (to omit many others,) are not, or at leaſt were Authentick Laws; if ſo, then the Kings of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> had Originally the Enacting Power in themſelves alone. Thoſe Statutes being (if I miſtake not,) created, and made by the Kings Supream <hi>Fiat</hi> and Authority only, without the formal phraſe, <hi>By and with the Conſent of,</hi> &amp;c. Though now thoſe words are look'd upon as Eſſential.</p>
            <p>This ſure is a great Prerogative of the <hi>Crown,</hi> and at any time may be re-aſſum'd if 'tis the Princes pleaſure ſo to do, for <hi>Nullum tempus occurrit Regi.</hi> And therefore, if Subjects will Sawcily Vindicate their <hi>pretended</hi> Rights and Properties, I ſee no Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why His Majeſty may not Legally Aſſert his own Power and Prerogative.</p>
            <p>Theſe, (as well as many other Reaſons now in <hi>Print,</hi>) one would think were ſufficient to perſwade any Rational Man to a Complyance with His Majeſty, for Aboliſhing the <hi>TEST,</hi> and other <hi>Penal Laws</hi> concerning <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if nothing will do, and Men will ſtill perſiſt in their Obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy, I ſhall leave them to reap the benefit of their own folly, and ever Pray that God Almighty wou'd Enable His Majeſty to Trample upon His Enemies, and bleſs Him with a Long and Proſperous Reign, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:50707:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
